<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3986 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4181 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4181.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4741 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4741.xml'>
    <!ENTITY yangspec PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-netmod-yang.xml'>
    <!ENTITY yangtypes PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-netmod-yang-types.xml'>
]>

<rfc category="informational" 
     docName="draft-ietf-netmod-yang-usage-01" 
     ipr="trust200811">

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="no" ?>
<?rfc inline="no" ?>
<?rfc editing="no" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc compact="no"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no"?>

 <front>
   <title abbrev="YANG Usage Guidelines">
     Guidelines for Authors and Reviewers of YANG Data Model Documents
   </title>
   <author fullname="Andy Bierman" initials="A.B."
	   surname="Bierman">
     <organization>Netconf Central</organization>
     <address>
       <postal>
	 <street></street>
	 <city>Simi Valley</city>
	 <region>CA</region>
	 <code></code>
	 <country>USA</country>
       </postal>
       <email>andy@netconfcentral.com</email>
     </address>
   </author>

   <date month="May" year="2009" />
   <area>Management</area>
   <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>
   <keyword>NETMOD</keyword>
   <keyword>NETCONF</keyword>
   <keyword>XML</keyword>
   <keyword>YANG</keyword>
   <abstract>
     <t>
       This memo provides guidelines for authors and reviewers
       of standards track specifications containing YANG
       data model modules.   Applicable
       portions may be used as a basis for reviews of other 
       YANG data model documents.  Recommendations and
       procedures are defined, which are intended to
       increase interoperability and usability
       of NETCONF implementations which utilize
       YANG data model modules.
     </t>
   </abstract>
 </front>

 <middle>
   <section title="Introduction">
     <t>
       The standardization of network configuration interfaces for use 
       with the <xref target="RFC4741">NETCONF</xref> protocol 
       requires a modular set of data models, which can be reused
       and extended over time.
     </t>
     <t>
       This document defines a set of usage guidelines for
       standards track documents containing 
       <xref target="I-D.ietf-netmod-yang">
       YANG</xref> data models.  It is similar to
       the MIB usage guidelines specification
       <xref target="RFC4181"/> in intent and structure.
     </t>
     <t>
       Many YANG constructs are defined as optional to use, such as
       the description clause.  However, in order to
       maximize interoperability of NETCONF implementations
       utilizing YANG data models, it is desirable to
       define a set of usage guidelines which may require
       a higher level of compliance than the minimum level
       defined in the YANG specification.
     </t>
     <t>
       <figure anchor="NETCONF_stack">
	 <artwork>
<![CDATA[

 The NETCONF stack can be conceptually partitioned into four layers.

       Layer                Example
      +-------------+   +--------------------+ +-------------------+
  (4) |   Content   |   | Configuration data | | Notification data |
      +-------------+   +--------------------+ +-------------------+
             |                    |                   |
      +-------------+   +-----------------+     +---------------+
  (3) | Operations  |   |  <edit-config>  |     |  <eventType>  |
      +-------------+   +-----------------+     +---------------+
             |                    |                   |
      +-------------+   +--------------------+  +----------------+
  (2) |     RPC     |   | <rpc>, <rpc-reply> |  | <notification> |
      +-------------+   +--------------------+  +----------------+
             |                    |                   |
      +-------------+       +--------------------------------+
  (1) |  Transport  |       |  BEEP, SSH, SSL, TLS, console  |
      |   Protocol  |       |                                |
      +-------------+       +--------------------------------+

]]>
	 </artwork>
       </figure>
     </t>

     <t>
       This document defines usage guidelines related to
       the NETCONF operations layer (3), and NETCONF
       content layer (4).
     </t>
   </section>

   <section title="Terminology">
     <section title="Requirements Notation">
       <t>
	 The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
	 "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
	 and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
	 described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
       </t>
     </section>
     <section title="NETCONF Terms">
       <t>
	 The following terms are defined in <xref target="RFC4741"/>
	 and are not redefined here:
	 <list style="symbols">
	   <t>agent</t>
	   <t>application</t>
	   <t>capabilities</t>
	   <t>manager</t>
	   <t>operation</t>
	   <t>RPC</t>
	 </list>
       </t>
     </section>
     <section title="YANG Terms">
       <t>
	 The following terms are defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-netmod-yang"/>
	 and are not redefined here:
	 <list style="symbols">
	   <t>data node</t>
	   <t>module</t>
	   <t>submodule</t>
	   <t>namespace</t>
	   <t>version</t>
	 </list>
       </t>
     </section>
     <section title="Terms">
       <t>
	 The following terms are used throughout this document:
	 <list style="symbols">
	   <t>
	     <b>module</b>:
	     Generic term for a YANG data model module or submodule.
	     When describing properties which are specific to submodules,
	     the term 'YANG submodule', or simply 'submodule' is used instead.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     Published Document:
	     A stable release of a module, usually contained in an RFC.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     Unpublished Document:
	     An unstable release of a module, usually contained in 
	     an Internet Draft.
	   </t>
	 </list>
       </t>
     </section>
   </section>

   <section title="General Documentation Guidelines" anchor="GenGuidelines">
     <t>
       YANG data model modules under review are likely to be 
       contained in Internet Drafts.   All guidelines for
       Internet Draft authors MUST be followed.  These
       guidelines are available online at:
     </t>
     <t>
       http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc-editor/instructions2authors.txt
     </t>

     <t>
       The following sections MUST be present in an Internet Draft
       containing a module:
       <list style="symbols">
	 <t>YANG data model boilerplate section</t>
	 <t>Narrative sections</t>
	 <t>Definitions section</t>
	 <t>Security Considerations section</t>
	 <t>IANA Considerations section</t>
	 <t>References section</t>
       </list>
     </t>

     <section title="YANG Data Model Boilerplate Section">
       <t>
	 This section MUST contain a verbatim copy of the latest approved
	 Internet-Standard Management Framework boilerplate, which is
	 available on-line at [ed: URL TBD].
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Narrative Sections">
       <t>
	 The narrative part MUST include an overview section that describes
	 the scope and field of application of the module(s) defined by the
	 specification and that specifies the relationship (if any) of these
	 modules to other standards, particularly to standards containing
	 other module modules.  The narrative part SHOULD include one or more
	 sections to briefly describe the structure of the modules defined
	 in the specification.
       </t>
       <t>
	 If the module(s) defined by the specification import definitions
	 from other modules (except for those defined in the 
	 <xref target="I-D.ietf-netmod-yang">YANG</xref> or
	 <xref target="I-D.ietf-netmod-yang-types">YANG Types</xref>
	 documents) or are always implemented in
	 conjunction with other modules, then those facts MUST be noted in
	 the overview section, as MUST any special interpretations of objects
	 in other modules.
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Definitions Section">
       <t>
	 This section contains the module(s) defined by the specification.
	 These modules MUST be written in YANG
	 <xref target="I-D.ietf-netmod-yang"/>.
       </t>
       <t>
	 See <xref target="YangGuidelines"/> for guidelines on YANG usage.
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Security Considerations Section">
       <t>
	 Each specification that defines one or more modules MUST contain
	 a section that discusses security considerations relevant to those
	 modules.  This section MUST be patterned after the latest approved
	 template (available at [ed: URL TBD]).
       </t>
       <t>
	 In particular, writable module objects that could be especially
	 disruptive if abused MUST be explicitly listed by name and the
	 associated security risks MUST be spelled out; similarly, readable
	 module objects that contain especially sensitive information or that
	 raise significant privacy concerns MUST be explicitly listed by name
	 and the reasons for the sensitivity/privacy concerns MUST be
	 explained. 
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="IANA Considerations Section">
       <t>
	 In order to comply with IESG policy as set forth in
	 http://www.ietf.org/ID-Checklist.html, every Internet-Draft that is
	 submitted to the IESG for publication MUST contain an IANA
	 Considerations section.  The requirements for this section vary
	 depending what actions are required of the IANA.
       </t>

       <section title="Documents that Create a New Name Space">
	 <t>
	   If an Internet-Draft defines a new name space that is to be
	   administered by the IANA, then the document MUST include an IANA
	   Considerations section, that specifies how the name space is to be
	   administered.
	 </t>
	 <t>
	   Specifically, if any YANG module namespace statement value contained
	   in the document is not already registered with IANA, then a
	   new YANG Namespace registry entry must be requested from the
	   IANA.  The YANG specification includes the procedure
           for this purpose in its IANA Considerations section.
	 </t>
       </section>

       <section title="Documents that Extend an Existing Name Space">
	 <t>
	   If an Internet-Draft defines any extensions to a YANG 
	   Namespace already administered by the IANA, 
	   then the document MUST include an IANA
	   Considerations section, specifies how the name space extension
	   is to be administered.
	 </t>
	 <t>
	   Specifically, if any YANG submodule belongs-to value contained
	   in the document is associated with a module that contains
	   a namespace statement value equal to a YANG Namespace 
	   already administered by the IANA, then the existing YANG Namespace
           must be updated to include the new submodule.
	 </t>
       </section>
     </section>

     <section title="Reference Sections">
       <t>
	 [ed: 2223bis text TBD]
       </t>
       <t>
	 For every import or include statement which appears in a module contained
	 in the specification, which identifies a module in a separate document,
	 a corresponding normative reference to that document MUST
	 appear in the Normative References section.  The reference MUST
	 correspond to the specific module version actually used within
	 the specification.
       </t>
       <t>
	 For every reference statement which appears in a module contained
	 in the specification, which identifies a separate document,
	 a corresponding normative reference to that document SHOULD
	 appear in the Normative References section.  The reference SHOULD
	 correspond to the specific document version actually used within
	 the specification.
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Copyright Notices">
       <t>
	 The proper copyright notices MUST be present in the module
	 description statement. [ed.: See RFC 4181, 3.7.  Exact
	 text for insertion is TBD.]
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Intellectual Property Section">
       <t>
	 The proper IPR statements MUST be present in the document,
	 according to the most current Internet Draft boilerplate.
	 [ed.: actual IETF IPR text reference TBD]
       </t>
     </section>

   </section>

   <section title="YANG Usage Guidelines" anchor="YangGuidelines">
     <t>
       In general, modules in IETF standards-track specifications MUST
       comply with all syntactic and semantic requirements of YANG.
       <xref target="I-D.ietf-netmod-yang"/>.
       The guidelines in this section are intended
       to supplement the YANG specification, which is
       intended to define a minimum set of conformance
       requirements.
     </t>
     <t>
       In order to promote interoperability and establish
       a set of practices based on previous experience,
       the following sections establish usage guidelines
       for specific YANG constructs.
     </t>
     <t>
       Only guidelines which clarify or restrict the
       minimum conformance requirements are included here.
     </t>

     <section title="Module Naming Conventions">
       <t>
	 Modules contained in standards track documents
	 SHOULD be named with the prefix 'ietf-'.
	 Other types of modules MUST NOT use the 'ietf-'
	 prefix string.
       </t>
       <t>
	 A distinctive word or acronym (e.g., protocol name
	 or working group acronym) SHOULD be used in the
	 module name.  If new definitions are being defined
	 to extend one or more existing modules, then the same
	 word or acronym should be reused, instead of
	 creating a new one.
       </t>
       <t>
	 All published module names MUST be unique.
       </t>
       <t>
	 Once a module name is published, it MUST not be reused,
	 even if the RFC containing the module is reclassified
	 to 'Historic' status.
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Identifiers">
       <t>
	 Identifiers for modules, submodules, typedefs,
	 groupings, data objects, rpcs, and notifications
	 MUST be between 1 and 64 characters in length.
       </t>
       <t>
     </section>

     <section title="Defaults">
       <t>
	 In general, it is suggested that sub-statements
	 containing default values SHOULD NOT be present.
	 For example, 'status current;', 
	 'config true;', 'mandatory false;',
	 and 'max-elements unbounded;'
	 are common defaults which would make the module difficult
	 to read if used everywhere they are allowed.
       </t>
       <t>
	 Instead, it is suggested that common 
	 statements SHOULD only be used when being set to a
	 value other than the default value.
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Conditional Statements">
       <t>
	 A module may be conceptually partitioned in several
	 ways, using the 'if-feature' and/or 'when' statements.
	 In addition, NETCONF capabilities are designed to
	 identify optional functionality.
       </t>
       <t>
	 Data model designers need to carefully consider all
	 modularity aspects, including the use of YANG conditional
	 statements.
       </t>
       <t>
	 Objects SHOULD NOT directly reference NETCONF capabilities,
	 in order to specify optional behavior.  Instead, a 'feature'
	 statement
	 SHOULD be defined to represent the NETCONF capability,
	 and the 'if-feature' statement SHOULD be used within
	 the object definition.
       </t>
       <t>
	 If the condition associated with the desired semantics
	 is not dependent on any particular instance value
	 within the database, then an 'if-feature' statement
	 SHOULD be used instead of a 'when' statement.
       </t>
       <t>
	 All 'must' and 'when' statements MUST contain valid XPath.
	 If any name tests are present, they MUST contain
	 valid module prefixes and data node names.
         References to non-existent nodes are considered invalid
         in YANG, even though they are permitted in XPath.
       </t>
       <t>
	 The 'attribute' and 'namespace' axis SHOULD NOT be used
	 because the associated XML node types are not supported in YANG,
	 and may not be supported consistently across NETCONF
         agent implementations.
       </t>
       <t>
	 The 'position' and 'last' functions SHOULD NOT be used.
	 Also, the 'preceding', 
	 and 'following' axes SHOULD NOT be used.
	 These constructs rely on XML document order within a NETCONF agent
	 configuration database, which may not be supported
	 consistently or produce reliable results across implementations.
	 Predicate expressions based on static node
	 properties (e.g., name, value, ancestors,
	 descendants) SHOULD be used instead.
       </t>
       <t>
         The 'preceding-sibling' and 'following-sibling' axes
         MAY be used, with causion.  An agent is not required to
         maintain a persistent or deterministic XML document
         order, which will affect use of these axes.
       <t>
	 Implicit 'position' function calls within predicates
	 SHOULD NOT be used. (e.g., //chapter[42]).
       </t>
       <t>
	 Data nodes which use the 'int64' and 'uint64' built-in
	 type SHOULD NOT be used within relational expressions.
	 There are boundary conditions in which the translation
	 from the YANG 64-bit type to an XPath number can cause
	 incorrect results.
       </t>
       <t>
	 Data modelers need to be careful not to
	 confuse the YANG value space and the XPath
	 value space.  The data types are not the same in both,
	 and conversion between YANG and XPath data types
	 SHOULD be considered carefully.
       </t>
       <t>
	 Explicit XPath data type conversions MAY be used
	 (e.g., 'string', 'boolean', or 'number' functions),
	 instead of implicit XPath data type conversions.
       </t>
     </section>


     <section title="Lifecycle Management">
       <t>
	 The status statement SHOULD NOT be present if its value
	 is 'current'.  It MUST be present if its value
	 is 'deprecated' or 'obsolete'.
       </t>
       <t>
	 The module or submodule name MUST NOT be changed, once
	 the document containing the module or submodule is published.
       </t>
       <t>
	 The module namespace URI value SHOULD NOT be changed,
	 once the document containing the module is published.
       </t>
       <t>
	 The revision-date sub-statement (within the imports
	 statement) SHOULD be present.
	 It MUST be present (in all published modules) if any
	 groupings are used from the external module.
       </t>
       <t>
	 The revision-date sub-statement (within the include
	 statement) MAY be present.
	 It SHOULD be present (in all published modules) if any
	 groupings are used from the external sub-module.
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Header Contents">
       <t>
	 <list style="symbols">
	   <t>
	     For published modules, the namespace MUST 
             be a globally unique
	     URI, as defined in <xref target="RFC3986"/>.
	     This value is usually assigned by the IANA.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     The organization statement MUST be present.
             If the module is contained in a documented
             intended for standards-track status, then
             the organization SHOULD be the IETF.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     The contact statement MUST be present.
             If the module is contained in a documented
             intended for standards-track status, then
             the working group WEB and mailing information
             MUST be present, and the document author
             contact information SHOULD be present.
             In addition, the Area Director and other contact
             information MAY be present.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     The description statement MUST be present.
	   </t>
           <t>
             If the module relies on information contained
             in other documents, which are not the same
             documents implied by the import statements
             present in the module, then these documents
             MUST be identified in the reference
             statement.
           </t>
           <t>
             A normative reference MUST be present in
             the references section of the document 
             for every module identified in an import
             statement.
           </t>
           <t>
             The document which contains the module SHOULD
             be identified in the reference statement,
             whether it is published or unpublished.
             Modules are often extracted from their original
             documents and it is useful for developers
             and operators to know how to find the
             original source document in a consistent manner.
           </t>
	   <t>
	     A revision statement MUST be present for each published
	     version of the module.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     Each new revision MUST include a revision date which
	     is higher than any other revision date in the module.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     It is acceptable to reuse the
	     same revision statement within unpublished versions
	     (i.e., Internet Drafts), but the revision date
	     MUST be updated to a higher value each time the
	     Internet Draft is re-published.
	   </t>
	 </list>
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Temporary Namespace Assignments">
       <t>
         It is desirable to include only valid YANG modules
         in documents, whether they are published yet or not.
         <list style="bullets">
           <t>
             allows the module to compile correctly instead 
             of generating disruptive fatal errors.
           </t>
           <t>
             allows early implementors to use the modules
             without picking a random value for this field.
           </t>
           <t>
             allows early interoperability testing since
             independent implementations will use the same
             namespace value.
           </t>
         </list>
       </t>
       <t>
         Until a URI is assigned by the IANA, a temporary namespace URI
         MUST be provided for the namespace statement in a YANG module.
         A value SHOULD be selected which is not likely to collide with 
         other YANG namespaces.
       </t>
       <t>
         An unpublished module namespace statement value SHOULD
         include the field 'DRAFT-nn', where 'nn' is replaced
         by the current Internet Draft number.
       </t>
       <t>
         If the YANG module has been previously published, then
         the RPC being updated needs to be identified.
         In this case, an unpublished module namespace statement value SHOULD
         include the field 'DRAFT-XXXXBIS-nn', where 'XXXX' is
         replaced by the RFC number being updated, and 'nn' is replaced
         by the current Internet Draft number.
       </t>
       <t>
         A temporary namespace statement value SHOULD have the
         following form:
         <br/><br/>
         &lt;URN prefix string&gt;:&lt;module-name&gt;:&lt;draft-field&gt;
       </t>
       <t>
         The suggested URN prefix string that SHOULD be used is shown below.
         This value will be defined by the IANA.<br/>
         urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:
       </t>
       <t>
         The following example URNs would be valid temporary namespace
         statement values:
         <list style="bullets">
           <t>
             urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-netconf-partial-lock:DRAFT-09
           </t>
           <t>
             urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-netconf-state:DRAFT-07
           </t>
           <t>
             urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-netconf:DRAFT-4741BIS-01
           </t>
         </list>
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Top Level Database Objects">
       <t>
         There SHOULD only be one top-level data node defined
         in each YANG module.  However, there MAY be more than one
         if needed.
       </t>
       <t>
         The top-level data organization SHOULD be considered carefully,
         in advance.  Data model designers need to consider how
         the functionality for a given protocol or protocol family
         will grow over time.
       </t>
       <t>
         The names and data organization SHOULD reflect persistent
         information, such as the name of a protocol.  The name
         of the working group SHOULD NOT be used because this
         may change over time.
       </t>
       <t>
         A mandatory database object is defined as 
         a node that a manager must provide for the database
         to be valid.  The agent will not provide a value
         under any conditions.
       </t>
       <t>
         Top-level database objects MUST NOT be mandatory.
       </t>
       <t>
         If a mandatory node appears at the top-level, it will 
         immediately cause the database to be invalid.
         This can occue when the agent boots or when a module
         is loaded dynamically at runtime.
       </t>
       <t>
         Top level objects are declared in YANG as mandatory with
         the mandatory statement or the min-elements statement.
         All nested non-presence containers are transparent,
         so a mandatory node nested within one or more non-presence
         containers causes the top-level container to
         be considered mandatory.
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Data Types">
       <t>
	 <list style="symbols">
	   <t>
	     Selection of an appropriate data type (i.e., built-in
	     type, existing derived type, or new derived type)
	     is very subjective and therefore few requirements
	     can be specified on that subject.  
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     Data model designers SHOULD use the most appropriate
	     built-in data type for the particular application.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     If extensibility of enumerated values is required,
	     then the identityref data type SHOULD be used
	     instead of an enumeration or other built-in type.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     For string data types, if a machine-readable pattern
	     can be defined for the desired semantics, then
	     one or more pattern statements SHOULD be present.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     For string data types, if the length of the string
	     is not required to be unbounded in all implementations,
	     then a length statement SHOULD be present.
	     [ed: should the 'resource-denied' error be mentioned here?]
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     For numeric data types, if the values allowed
	     by the intended semantics are different than
	     those allowed by the unbounded intrinsic data 
	     type (e.g., int32), then a range statement SHOULD be present.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     The signed numeric data types (i.e., 'int8',
	     'int16', 'int32', and 'int64') SHOULD NOT be used unless
	     negative values are allowed for the desired semantics.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     For enumeration or bits data types, the semantics for
	     each enum or bit SHOULD be documented.  A separate
	     description statement (within each enum or bit
	     statement) SHOULD be present.
	   </t>
	 </list>
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Reusable Type Definitions">
       <t>
	 <list style="symbols">
	   <t>
	     If an appropriate derived type exists in any
	     standard module, such as <xref target="I-D.ietf-netmod-yang-types"/>,
	     then it SHOULD be used instead of defining a new derived type.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     If an appropriate units identifier can be associated
	     with the desired semantics, then a units statement
	     SHOULD be present.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     If an appropriate default value can be associated
	     with the desired semantics, then a default statement
	     SHOULD be present.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     If a significant number of derived types are defined,
	     and it is anticipated that these data types will be reused
	     by multiple modules, then these derived types SHOULD be
	     contained in a separate module or submodule, to allow
	     easier reuse without unnecessary coupling.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     The description statement MUST be present.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     If the type definition semantics are defined
	     in an external document, then the reference
	     statement SHOULD be present.
	   </t>
	 </list>
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Object Definitions">
       <t>
	 <list style="symbols">
	   <t>
	     The description statement MUST be present in the following
	     body statements:
	     <list style="symbols">
	       <t>extension</t>
	       <t>feature</t>	     
	       <t>identity</t>
	       <t>typedef</t>
	       <t>grouping</t>
	       <t>augment</t>
	       <t>rpc</t>
	       <t>notification</t>
	     </list>
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     The description statement MUST be present in the following
	     data definition constructs:
	     <list style="symbols">
	       <t>container</t>
	       <t>leaf</t>
	       <t>leaf-list</t>
	       <t>list</t>
	       <t>choice</t>
	       <t>anyxml</t>
	     </list>
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     If the object semantics are defined in an external document,
	     then a reference statement SHOULD be present.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     The 'anyxml' construct MUST NOT be used within
	     configuration data.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     If there are referential integrity constraints associated
	     with the desired semantics that
	     can be represented with XPath, then one or more
	     must statements SHOULD be present.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     For list and leaf-list objects, if the number of possible instances
	     is not required to be unbounded for all implementations, 
	     then the max-elements statement SHOULD be present.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     If any must or when statements are used within the
	     object definition, then the object description statement
	     SHOULD describe the purpose of each one.
	   </t>
	 </list>
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="RPC Definitions">
       <t>
	 <list style="symbols">
	   <t>
	     The description statement MUST be present.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     If the RPC method semantics are defined in an external document,
	     then a reference statement SHOULD be present.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     If the RPC method impacts system behavior in some way,
	     it SHOULD be mentioned in the description statement.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     If the RPC method is potentially harmful to system 
	     behavior in some way,
	     it MUST be mentioned in the Security Considerations
	     section of the document.
	   </t>
	 </list>
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Notification Definitions">
       <t>
	 <list style="symbols">
	   <t>
	     The description statement MUST be present.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     If the notification semantics are defined in an external document,
	     then a reference statement SHOULD be present.
	   </t>
	 </list>
       </t>
     </section>
   </section>

   <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

   <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
    <t>
      There are no actions requested of IANA at this time.
    </t>
   </section>

  <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
    <t>
      This document defines documentation guidelines for
      NETCONF content defined with the YANG data modeling
      language.  It does not introduce
      any new or increased security risks into 
      the management system.
      [ed: RFC 4181 style security section TBD]
    </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Acknowledgments">
    <t>
      The structure and contents of this document are adapted from
      <xref target="RFC4181">
	Guidelines for MIB Documents
	</xref>, by C. M. Heard.
    </t>
  </section>

</middle>

  <!--  ***** BACK MATTER ***** -->
  <back>
   <references title="Normative References">
     &rfc2119;
     &rfc3986;
     &rfc4741;
     &yangspec;
     &yangtypes;
   </references>
   <references title="Informative References">
     &rfc4181;
   </references>

   <appendix title="Module Review Checklist">
     <t>
       This section is adapted from RFC 4181.
     </t>
     <t>
       The purpose of a YANG module review is to review 
       the YANG module both for technical correctness and
       for adherence to IETF documentation requirements.
       The following checklist may be helpful when reviewing
       a draft document:
     </t>
     <list style="numbers">
       <t>
	 <b>I-D Boilerplate</b> -- 
	 verify that the draft contains the required
	 Internet-Draft boilerplate 
	 (see http://www.ietf.org/ietf/1id-guidelines.txt), 
	 including the appropriate statement to permit
	 publication as an RFC, and that I-D boilerplate does 
	 not contain references or section numbers.
       </t>
       <t><b>Abstract</b>
       -- verify that the abstract does not contain references,
       that it does not have a section number, and that its content follows
       the guidelines in http://www.ietf.org/ietf/1id-guidelines.txt.
       </t>
       <t>
	 <b>YANG Module Boilerplate</b> -- 
	 verify that the draft contains the latest
	 approved SNMP Network Management Framework boilerplate from the OPS
	 area web site (http://www.ops.ietf.org/mib-boilerplate.html).
	 [ed: real URL TBD]
       </t>
       <t>
	 <b>Security Considerations Section</b>
	 -- verify that the draft uses the
	 latest approved template from the OPS area web site
	 (http://www.ops.ietf.org/mib-security.html) and that the guidelines
	 therein have been followed.
       </t>
       <t>
	 <b>IANA Considerations Section</b>
	 -- this section must always be
	 present.  If the draft requires no action from the IANA, ensure that
	 this is explicitly noted.  If the draft requires URI values to be
	 assigned, ensure that the IANA Considerations section contains the
	 information specified in [TBD] of these guidelines.  If the
	 draft contains the initial version of an IANA-maintained module,
	 verify that the [TBD] invocation contains maintenance
	 instructions that comply with the requirements in RFC 2434.  In the
	 latter case, the IANA Considerations section that will appear in the
	 RFC MUST contain a pointer to the actual IANA-maintained module.
       </t>
       <t>
	 <b>References</b>
	 -- verify that the references are properly divided
	 between normative and informative references, that RFC 2119 is
	 included as a normative reference if the terminology defined therein
	 is used in the document, that all references required by the
	 boilerplate are present, that all YANG modules containing imported
	 items are cited as normative references, and that all citations point
	 to the most current RFCs unless there is a valid reason to do
	 otherwise (for example, it is OK to include an informative reference
	 to a previous version of a specification to help explain a feature
	 included for backward compatibility).
       </t>
       <t>
	 <b>Copyright Notices</b>
	 -- verify that the draft contains an
	 abbreviated copyright notice in the description statement of each
	 YANG module or sub-module, and that it contains the full copyright
	 notice and disclaimer specified in Sections 5.4 and 5.5 of RFC 3978
	 at the end of the document.  Make sure that the correct year is used
	 in all copyright dates.
       </t>
       <t>
	 <b>IPR Notice</b>
	 -- if the draft does not contains a verbatim copy of
	 the IPR notice specified in Section 5 of RFC 3979, recommend that the
	 IPR notice be included.
       </t>
       <t>
	 <b>Other Issues</b>
	 -- check for any issues mentioned in
	 http://www.ietf.org/ID-Checklist.html that are not covered elsewhere.
       </t>
       <t>
	 <b>Technical Content</b>
	 -- review the actual technical content for
	 compliance with the guidelines in this document.  The use of a YANG
	 module compiler is recommended when checking for syntax errors; see
	 [YANG tool URL TBD] for more information.
	 Checking for correct syntax, however, is only part of the job.  It is
	 just as important to actually read the YANG module document 
	 from the point of view of a potential implementor. 
	 It is particularly important to
	 check that description statements are sufficiently
	 clear and unambiguous to allow interoperable 
	 implementations to be created.
       </t>
     </list>
   </appendix>

   <appendix title="Change Log">
     <section title="Changes from -00 to -01">
       <list style="bullets">
         <t>
           Added TLS to figure 1.
         </t>
         <t>  
           Corrected URL for RPC instructions.
         </t>
         <t>
           Updated namespace procedures section.
         </t>
         <t>
           Updated details on module contact and organization
           statements.
         </t>
         <t>
           Created separate note on use of preseding-sibling
           and following-sibling axes in XPath expressions.
         </t>
         <t>
           Added section on temporary namespace statement values.
         </t>
         <t>
            Added section on top level database objects.
         </t>
         <t>  
           Fixed typos.
         </t>
       </list>
     </section>
   </appendix>
 </back>
</rfc>

