<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4181 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4181.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4741 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4741.xml'>
    <!ENTITY yangspec PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-netmod-yang.xml'>
    <!ENTITY yangtypes PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-netmod-yang-types.xml'>
]>

<rfc category="informational" 
     docName="draft-bierman-netmod-yang-usage-01" 
     ipr="trust200811">

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="no" ?>
<?rfc inline="no" ?>
<?rfc editing="no" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc compact="no"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no"?>

 <front>
   <title abbrev="YANG Usage Guidelines">
     Guidelines for Authors and Reviewers of YANG Data Model Documents
   </title>
   <author fullname="Andy Bierman" initials="A.B."
	   surname="Bierman">
     <organization>Netconf Central</organization>
     <address>
       <postal>
	 <street></street>
	 <city>Simi Valley</city>
	 <region>CA</region>
	 <code></code>
	 <country>USA</country>
       </postal>
       <email>andy@netconfcentral.com</email>
     </address>
   </author>

   <date month="May" year="2009" />
   <area>Management</area>
   <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>
   <keyword>NETMOD</keyword>
   <keyword>NETCONF</keyword>
   <keyword>XML</keyword>
   <keyword>YANG</keyword>
   <abstract>
     <t>
       This memo provides guidelines for authors and reviewers
       of standards track specifications containing YANG
       data model modules.   Applicable
       portions may be used as a basis for reviews of other 
       YANG data model documents.  Recommendations and
       procedures are defined, which are intended to
       increase interoperability and usability
       of NETCONF implementations which utilize
       YANG data model modules.
     </t>
   </abstract>
 </front>

 <middle>
   <section title="Introduction">
     <t>
       The standardization of network configuration interfaces for use 
       with the <xref target="RFC4741">NETCONF</xref> protocol 
       requires a modular set of data models, which can be reused
       and extended over time.
     </t>
     <t>
       This document defines a set of usage guidelines for
       standards track documents containing 
       <xref target="I-D.ietf-netmod-yang">
       YANG</xref> data models.  It is similar to
       the MIB usage guidelines specification
       <xref target="RFC4181"/> in intent and structure.
     </t>
     <t>
       Many YANG constructs are defined as optional to use, such as
       the description clause.  However, in order to
       maximize interoperability of NETCONF implementations
       utilizing YANG data models, it is desirable to
       define a set of usage guidelines which may require
       a higher level of compliance than the minimum level
       defined in the YANG specification.
     </t>
     <t>
       <figure anchor="NETCONF_stack">
	 <artwork>
<![CDATA[

 The NETCONF stack can be conceptually partitioned into four layers.

       Layer                Example
      +-------------+   +--------------------+ +-------------------+
  (4) |   Content   |   | Configuration data | | Notification data |
      +-------------+   +--------------------+ +-------------------+
             |                    |                   |
      +-------------+   +-----------------+     +---------------+
  (3) | Operations  |   |  <edit-config>  |     |  <eventType>  |
      +-------------+   +-----------------+     +---------------+
             |                    |                   |
      +-------------+   +--------------------+  +----------------+
  (2) |     RPC     |   | <rpc>, <rpc-reply> |  | <notification> |
      +-------------+   +--------------------+  +----------------+
             |                    |                   |
      +-------------+       +-----------------------------+
  (1) |  Transport  |       |   BEEP, SSH, SSL, console   |
      |   Protocol  |       |                             |
      +-------------+       +-----------------------------+

]]>
	 </artwork>
       </figure>
     </t>

     <t>
       This document defines usage guidelines related to
       the NETCONF operations layer (3), and NETCONF
       content layer (4).
     </t>
   </section>

   <section title="Terminology">
     <section title="Requirements Notation">
       <t>
	 The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
	 "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
	 and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
	 described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
       </t>
     </section>
     <section title="NETCONF Terms">
       <t>
	 The following terms are defined in <xref target="RFC4741"/>
	 and are not redefined here:
	 <list style="symbols">
	   <t>agent</t>
	   <t>application</t>
	   <t>capabilities</t>
	   <t>manager</t>
	   <t>operation</t>
	   <t>RPC</t>
	 </list>
       </t>
     </section>
     <section title="YANG Terms">
       <t>
	 The following terms are defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-netmod-yang"/>
	 and are not redefined here:
	 <list style="symbols">
	   <t>data node</t>
	   <t>module</t>
	   <t>submodule</t>
	   <t>namespace</t>
	   <t>version</t>
	 </list>
       </t>
     </section>
     <section title="Terms">
       <t>
	 The following terms are used throughout this document:
	 <list style="symbols">
	   <t>
	     <b>module</b>:
	     Generic term for a YANG data model module or submodule.
	     When describing properties which are specific to submodules,
	     the term 'YANG submodule', or simply 'submodule' is used instead.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     Published Document:
	     A stable release of a module, usually contained in an RFC.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     Unpublished Document:
	     An unstable release of a module, usually contained in 
	     an Internet Draft.
	   </t>
	 </list>
       </t>
     </section>
   </section>

   <section title="General Documentation Guidelines" anchor="GenGuidelines">
     <t>
       YANG data model modules under review are likely to be 
       contained in Internet Drafts.   All guidelines for
       Internet Draft authors MUST be followed.  These
       guidelines are available online at:
     </t>
     <t>
       http://www.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc-editor/instructions2authors.txt
     </t>

     <t>
       The following sections MUST be present in an Internet Draft
       containing a module:
       <list style="symbols">
	 <t>YANG data model boilerplate section</t>
	 <t>Narrative sections</t>
	 <t>Definitions section</t>
	 <t>Security Considerations section</t>
	 <t>IANA Considerations section</t>
	 <t>References section</t>
       </list>
     </t>

     <section title="YANG Data Model Boilerplate Section">
       <t>
	 This section MUST contain a verbatim copy of the latest approved
	 Internet-Standard Management Framework boilerplate, which is
	 available on-line at [ed: URL TBD].
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Narrative Sections">
       <t>
	 The narrative part MUST include an overview section that describes
	 the scope and field of application of the module(s) defined by the
	 specification and that specifies the relationship (if any) of these
	 modules to other standards, particularly to standards containing
	 other module modules.  The narrative part SHOULD include one or more
	 sections to briefly describe the structure of the modules defined
	 in the specification.
       </t>
       <t>
	 If the module(s) defined by the specification import definitions
	 from other modules (except for those defined in the 
	 <xref target="I-D.ietf-netmod-yang">YANG</xref> or
	 <xref target="I-D.ietf-netmod-yang-types">YANG Types</xref>
	 documents) or are always implemented in
	 conjunction with other modules, then those facts MUST be noted in
	 the overview section, as MUST any special interpretations of objects
	 in other modules.
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Definitions Section">
       <t>
	 This section contains the module(s) defined by the specification.
	 These modules MUST be written in YANG
	 <xref target="I-D.ietf-netmod-yang"/>.
       </t>
       <t>
	 See <xref target="YangGuidelines"/> for guidelines on YANG usage.
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Security Considerations Section">
       <t>
	 Each specification that defines one or more modules MUST contain
	 a section that discusses security considerations relevant to those
	 modules.  This section MUST be patterned after the latest approved
	 template (available at [ed: URL TBD]).
       </t>
       <t>
	 In particular, writable module objects that could be especially
	 disruptive if abused MUST be explicitly listed by name and the
	 associated security risks MUST be spelled out; similarly, readable
	 module objects that contain especially sensitive information or that
	 raise significant privacy concerns MUST be explicitly listed by name
	 and the reasons for the sensitivity/privacy concerns MUST be
	 explained. 
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="IANA Considerations Section">
       <t>
	 In order to comply with IESG policy as set forth in
	 http://www.ietf.org/ID-Checklist.html, every Internet-Draft that is
	 submitted to the IESG for publication MUST contain an IANA
	 Considerations section.  The requirements for this section vary
	 depending what actions are required of the IANA.
       </t>

       <section title="Documents that Create a New Name Space">
	 <t>
	   If an Internet-Draft defines a new name space that is to be
	   administered by the IANA, then the document MUST include an IANA
	   Considerations section, specifies how the name space is to be
	   administered.
	 </t>
	 <t>
	   Specifically, if any YANG module namespace statement value contained
	   in the document is not already registered with IANA, then a
	   new YANG Namespace registry entry must be requested from the
	   IANA [ed: procedure TBD].
	 </t>
       </section>

       <section title="Documents that Extend an Existing Name Space">
	 <t>
	   If an Internet-Draft defines any extensions to a YANG 
	   Namespace already administered by the IANA, 
	   then the document MUST include an IANA
	   Considerations section, specifies how the name space extension
	   is to be administered.
	 </t>
	 <t>
	   Specifically, if any YANG submodule belongs-to value contained
	   in the document is associated with a module that contains
	   a namespace statement value equal to a YANG Namespace 
	   already administered by the IANA, then a new YANG Module registry
	   entry and YANG Namespace Update Procedure must be requested from the
	   IANA [ed: procedure TBD].
	 </t>
       </section>
     </section>

     <section title="Reference Sections">
       <t>
	 [ed: 2223bis text TBD]
       </t>
       <t>
	 For every import or include statement which appears in a module contained
	 in the specification, which identifies a module in a separate document,
	 a corresponding normative reference to that document MUST
	 appear in the Normative References section.  The reference MUST
	 correspond to the specific module version actually used within
	 the specification.
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Copyright Notices">
       <t>
	 The proper copyright notices MUST be present in the module
	 description statement. [ed.: See RFC 4181, 3.7.  Exact
	 text for insertion is TBD.]
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Intellectual Property Section">
       <t>
	 The proper IPR statements MUST be present in the document,
	 according to the most current Internet Draft boilerplate.
	 [ed.: actual IETF IPR text reference TBD]
       </t>
     </section>

   </section>

   <section title="YANG Usage Guidelines" anchor="YangGuidelines">
     <t>
       In general, modules in IETF standards-track specifications MUST
       comply with all syntactic and semantic requirements of YANG.
       <xref target="I-D.ietf-netmod-yang"/>.
       The guidelines in this section are intended
       to supplement the YANG specification, which is
       intended to define a minimum set of conformance
       requirements.
     </t>
     <t>
       In order to promote interoperability and establish
       a set of practices based on previous experience,
       the following sections establish usage guidelines
       for specific YANG constructs.
     </t>
     <t>
       Only guidelines which clarify or restrict the
       minimum conformance requirements are included here.
     </t>

     <section title="Identifiers">
       <t>
	 Identifiers for modules, submodules, typedefs,
	 groupings, data objects, rpcs, and notifications
	 MUST be between 1 and 63 characters in length.
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Defaults">
       <t>
	 In general, it is suggested that sub-statements
	 containing default values SHOULD NOT be present.
	 For example, 'status current;', 
	 'config true;', 'mandatory false;',
	 and 'max-elements unbounded;'
	 are common defaults which would make the module difficult
	 to read if used everywhere they are allowed.
       </t>
       <t>
	 Instead, it is suggested that common 
	 statements SHOULD only be used when being set to a
	 value other than the default value.
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Conditional Statements">
       <t>
	 A module may be conceptually partitioned in several
	 ways, using the 'if-feature' and/or 'when' statements.
	 In addition, NETCONF capabilities are designed to
	 identify optional functionality.
       </t>
       <t>
	 Data model designers need to carefully consider all
	 modularity aspects, including the use of YANG conditional
	 statements.
       </t>
       <t>
	 Objects SHOULD NOT directly reference NETCONF capabilities,
	 in order to specify optional behavior.  Instead, a 'feature'
	 statement
	 SHOULD be defined to represent the NETCONF capability,
	 and the 'if-feature' statement SHOULD be used within
	 the object definition.
       </t>
       <t>
	 If the condition associated with the desired semantics
	 is not dependent on any particular instance value
	 within the database, then an 'if-feature' statement
	 SHOULD be used instead of a 'when' statement.
       </t>
       <t>
	 All 'must' and 'when' statements MUST contain valid XPath.
	 If any name tests are present, they MUST contain
	 valid module prefixes and/or data node names.
       </t>
       <t>
	 The 'attribute', 'namespace', 'preceding', 
	 'preceding-sibling', 'following',
	 and 'following-sibling' axis SHOULD NOT be used.
       </t>
       <t>
	 The 'position' and 'last' functions SHOULD NOT be used.
       </t>
       <t>
	 Implicit 'position' function calls within predicates
	 SHOULD NOT be used. (e.g., //chapter[42]).
       </t>
       <t>
	 Data nodes which use the 'int64' and 'uint64' built-in
	 type SHOULD NOT be used within relational expressions.
       </t>
       <t>
	 Data modelers need to be careful not to
	 confuse the YANG value space and the XPath
	 value space.  The data types are not the same in both,
	 and conversion between YANG and XPath data types
	 SHOULD be considered carefully.
       </t>
       <t>
	 Explicit XPath data type conversions SHOULD be used
	 (e.g., 'string', 'boolean', or 'number' functions),
	 instead of implicit XPath data type conversions.
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Header Contents">
       <t>
	 <list style="symbols">
	   <t>
	     The namespace MUST be a globally unique
	     URI, usually assigned by the IANA.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     Until a URI is assigned by the IANA, 
	     a temporary namespace string
	     SHOULD be selected which is not likely to
	     collide with other YANG namespaces, such as
	     the filename of the Internet Draft containing
	     the module.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     The organization statement MUST be present.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     The contact statement MUST be present.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     The description statement MUST be present.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     If the module represents a model defined in one or more
	     external documents, then a reference statement SHOULD
	     be present.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     A revision statement MUST be present for each published
	     version of the module.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     Each new revision MUST include a revision date which
	     is higher than any other revision date in the module.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     It is acceptable to reuse the
	     same revision statement within unpublished versions
	     (i.e., Internet Drafts), but the revision date
	     MUST be updated to a higher value each time the
	     Internet Draft is re-published.
	   </t>
	 </list>
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Data Types">
       <t>
	 <list style="symbols">
	   <t>
	     Selection of an appropriate data type (i.e., built-in
	     type, existing derived type, or new derived type)
	     is very subjective and therefore few requirements
	     can be specified on that subject.  
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     Data model designers SHOULD use the most appropriate
	     built-in data type for the particular application.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     If extensibility of enumerated values is required,
	     then the identityref data type SHOULD be used
	     instead of an enumeration or other built-in type.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     If an appropriate derived type exists in any
	     standard module, such as <xref target="I-D.ietf-netmod-yang-types"/>,
	     then it SHOULD be used instead of defining a new derived type.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     The description statement MUST be present.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     If the type semantics are defined in an external document,
	     then a reference statement SHOULD be present.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     For string data types, if a machine-readable pattern
	     can be defined for the desired semantics, then
	     one or more pattern statements SHOULD be present.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     For string data types, if the length of the string
	     is not unbounded in all implementations,
	     then a length statement SHOULD be present.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     For numeric data types, if the values allowed
	     by the intended semantics are different than
	     those allowed by the unbounded intrinsic data 
	     type (e.g., int32), then a range statement SHOULD be present.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     The signed numeric data types (i.e., 'int8',
	     'int16', 'int32', and 'int64') SHOULD NOT be used unless
	     negative values are allowed for the desired semantics.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     The 'float32' and 'float64' data types SHOULD only
	     be used if the other numeric data types do not
	     fully represent the desired semantics.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     For enumeration or bits data types, the semantics for
	     each enum or bit SHOULD be documented.  A separate
	     description statement (within each enum or bit
	     statement) SHOULD be used, instead of the description
	     statement for the type itself.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     If an appropriate units identifier can be associated
	     with the desired semantics, then a units statement
	     SHOULD be present.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     If an appropriate default value can be associated
	     with the desired semantics, then a default statement
	     SHOULD be present.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     If a significant number of derived types are defined,
	     and it is anticipated that these data types will be reused
	     by multiple modules, then these derived types SHOULD be
	     contained in a separate module or submodule, to allow
	     easier reuse without unnecessary coupling.
	   </t>
	 </list>
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Object Definitions">
       <t>
	 <list style="symbols">
	   <t>
	     The description statement MUST be present.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     If the object semantics are defined in an external document,
	     then a reference statement SHOULD be present.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     The 'anyxml' construct MUST NOT be used within
	     configuration data.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     If there are referential integrity constraints associated
	     with the desired semantics that
	     can be represented with XPath, then one or more
	     must statements SHOULD be present.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     For list and leaf-list objects, if the number of possible instances
	     for all implementations is not unbounded, then the min-elements and/or
	     max-elements statements SHOULD be present.
	   </t>
	 </list>
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="RPC Definitions">
       <t>
	 <list style="symbols">
	   <t>
	     The description statement MUST be present.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     If the RPC method semantics are defined in an external document,
	     then a reference statement SHOULD be present.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     If the RPC method impacts system behavior in some way,
	     it SHOULD be mentioned in the description statement.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     If the RPC method is potentially harmful to system behavior in some way,
	     it MUST be mentioned in the Security Considerations
	     section of the document.
	   </t>
	 </list>
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Notification Definitions">
       <t>
	 <list style="symbols">
	   <t>
	     The description statement MUST be present.
	   </t>
	   <t>
	     If the notification semantics are defined in an external document,
	     then a reference statement SHOULD be present.
	   </t>
	 </list>
       </t>
     </section>
   </section>

   <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

   <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
    <t>
      There are no actions requested of IANA at this time.
    </t>
   </section>

  <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
    <t>
      This document defines documentation guidelines for
      NETCONF content defined with the YANG data modeling
      language.  It does not introduce
      any new or increased security risks into 
      the management system.
      [ed: RFC 4181 style security section TBD]
    </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Acknowledgments">
    <t>
      The structure and contents of this document are adapted from
      <xref target="RFC4181">
	Guidelines for MIB Documents
	</xref>, by C. M. Heard.
    </t>
  </section>

</middle>

  <!--  ***** BACK MATTER ***** -->
  <back>
   <references title="Normative References">
     &rfc2119;
     &rfc4741;
     &yangspec;
     &yangtypes;
   </references>
   <references title="Informative References">
     &rfc4181;
   </references>

 </back>

</rfc>

